<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter sent from the Right Honorable Robert Earle of Warwik, admirall of the sea; to Mr. Iohn Pim, Esquire; and by him presented by both House of Parliament, Iuly 6, 1642. Mercurii, 6 Iulii. 1642. Ordered by the Lords in Parliament, that this letter be forthwith printed and published. Jo. Brown. Cleric. Parliamentorum.</title>
            <author>Warwick, Robert Rich, Earl of, 1587-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96049</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1004</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E154_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20481</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864272</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864272</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116497</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96049)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116497)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 27:E154[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter sent from the Right Honorable Robert Earle of Warwik, admirall of the sea; to Mr. Iohn Pim, Esquire; and by him presented by both House of Parliament, Iuly 6, 1642. Mercurii, 6 Iulii. 1642. Ordered by the Lords in Parliament, that this letter be forthwith printed and published. Jo. Brown. Cleric. Parliamentorum.</title>
                  <author>Warwick, Robert Rich, Earl of, 1587-1658.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Lords.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5, [1] p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. G. for I. Hunscot and I. Wright,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page vignette = a portrait of Warwick.</note>
                  <note>The author states his intention to continue serving Parliament.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Warwick, Robert Rich, --  Earl of, 1587-1658.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116497:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116497:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Letter ſent from the Right Honorable ROBERT Earle of <hi>Warwik,</hi> Admirall of the Sea; to Mr. <hi>Iohn Pim,</hi> Eſquire; and by him preſented by both Houſe of PARLIAMENT, <hi>Iuly</hi> 6. 1642.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Mercurii 6 <hi>Iulii.</hi> 1642.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>ORdered by the Lords in Parliament, That this Letter be forthwith printed and publiſhed.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Jo. Brown Cleric. Parliamentorum.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of Sir Robert Rich, second Earl of Warwick (1587-1658)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E.G.</hi> for <hi>I. Hunſcot</hi> and <hi>I. Wright.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:116497:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116497:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Maſter PIM.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore theſe ſhall come to your hand, I make no doubt but Maſter <hi>Nicholls</hi> of the Houſe of Commons, hath made both Houſes a Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what hath paſſed here ſince I received his Majeſties Letters for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging me of the command of the Fleet, whereby I was entruſted; Now I called a Counſell of Warre, and acquainted them with his Majeſties Letters, and likewiſe with the Ordinance of Parliament ſent from the Houſes for mee to continue my charg, I confeſſe it was a great ſtreight that I was put in betweene two commands that have ſo much power over mee, but when
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116497:3"/>I conſider the great care which I have ever obſerved in the Parliaments of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for the good and ſafety of the King and Kingdome, and every mans particular in them, and that they are that great coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell by whoſe authority the Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> have ever ſpoken to their Subjects; And likewiſe that the truſt of this Fleete for the defence of his Majeſty, and the Kingdomes was committed to me, by them, and knowing the integrity of my owne heart to his Majeſty, and Parliament, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved not to deſert that charge commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to my truſt wherein God (bleſſed be his Name for it) hath made mee hitherto ſo ſucceſſefull; but to continue it untill I ſhall bee revoked by that authority that hath entruſted mee with it; which having declared to my Captaines at the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Warre, all of them unanimouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and cheerefully tooke the ſame reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution excepting five, which was the Reare Admirall, Captaine <hi>Fogge,</hi> Captaine <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> Captaine <hi>Slingsby</hi> and Captaine <hi>Wake:</hi> All which five refuſed to come upon my
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116497:3"/>Summons, as having no authority over them, and got together round that night to make their defence againſt mee, onely Captaine <hi>Burley</hi> came in, and ſubmitted to me, whereupon in the morning I weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Anchors, and cauſed the reſt of my Ships ſo to doe, and came to an Anchor round about them, and beſieged them, and when I had made all things ready I ſummoned them, Sir <hi>Iohn Mennes</hi> and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Fogge</hi> came in to mee, but Captaine <hi>Slingsby,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Wake</hi> ſtood out, whereupon I let fly a Gun over them, and ſent them word I had turned up the Glaſſe upon them, if in that ſpace they came not in they muſt looke for mee aboard them, I ſent to them by my Boat, and moſt of the Boats in the Fleete, their anſwer was ſo peremptory that my Maſters, and Saylors grew ſo impatient on them, that although they had no Armes in their Boates, at all yet God gave them ſuch courage, and reſolution, as in a moment they entred them, tooke hold on their ſhrouds and ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed upon theſe Captaines being armed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116497:4"/>with their Piſtols and Swords, and ſtrooke their Yards and Top-maſts and brought them both to me; the like courage and reſolution was never ſeene amongſt unar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med men, ſo as all was ended without effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of blood, which I muſt attribute to the great God of Heaven and Earth onely, who in the moment that I was ready to give fire on them, put ſuch courage into our men to act it, and ſo ſaved much blood. I hope the Parliament will thinke of ſome courſe for all our Indempnities, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for the officers of the Navy, and principall for the Surveyour of the Navy, my Vice-Admirall, a very able and good man; For my ſelfe I doubt not but they that put me in this imployment will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve me for ſerving them faithfully.</p>
            <p>I pray you Sir, be a meanes to Sir <hi>Robert Pie,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Greene,</hi> that ſome money may be ſent us, for it hath beene often promiſed but we heare not of it. The weather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing ſtormy ſo long together, that we ſpend our Maſts and Top-maſts, or ſome determent or other fals upon us daily, ſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116497:4"/>that we are in great extremity for want of money. Thus having nothing elſe to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you for the preſent, onely that you will be pleaſed to acquaint your Houſe of Commons with our proceedings, here I bid you farewell, and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your aſſured Friend, WARVVICK,</signed>
               <dateline>From aboard His Majeſties Ship the <hi>Iames</hi> in the <hi>Downs</hi> 
                  <date>this 4. of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
